Guide to the New York City COVID-19 Web Activism Collection TAM.798
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Make The Road: Our COVID Response, May 2020-ongoing; Make the Road (New York) (Box Electronic Records)
  Make the Road New York is a grassroots immigrant and workers organization. They focus on education equity; health justice; housing and environmental justice; policing and criminal justice; transgender, gender non-conforming, intersex, and queer justice; and workplace justice. During the COVID-19 pandemic, they established an emergency response fund; held know your rights trainings; promoted advocacy campaigns related to an eviction moratorium and immigration enforcement; workers rights resources related to safety, paid sick leave, and unemployment; immigrant rights resources; the Emergency Rental Assistance program; and health and food program resources.
- Covid-19 Impact on Household Cleaners in NYC, April 2022; Make the Road (New York) (Box Electronic Records)
  This report, compiled by Make the Road New York, presents data on the impact of COVID-19 on household cleaners in New York City and Westchester conducted between March 2021 and June 2021.
- Till We're Excluded No More: Short Documentary, August 2022; Make the Road (New York) (Box Electronic Records)
  Short video documenting the excluded workers march to Albany in March 2022.
- The Most Beautiful Home..Maybe, July 2023; Mark-n-Sparks, Inc. (Box Electronic Records)
  A multicity project that aims to use art to influence housing policy, created by Mark-n-Sparks (ashley sparks and Mark Valdez). A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- Immigrant Accompaniment Networks & COVID-19, June 2020-February 2022; Metrowest Worker Center (Box Electronic Records)
  Google document linked from the SWOP Brooklyn website's COVID resource page related to immigrant justice; racism and COVID-19; immigration court; COVID vulnerability in immigration detention centers and prisons and jails; and protest information.
- Memorial Crane Project Instagram, July-August 2023; Memorial Crane Project (Box Electronic Records)
  Instagram for the Memorial Crane Project, a collaborative memorial art project and nonprofit honoring COVID victims. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- COVID, Commemoration, and Cultural Memory, July 2023; Modernist Studies Association (Box Electronic Records)
  Article by Alice Kelly in Modernism/modernity. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- Memorials to COVID-19 Must Hold Space for Grief and Accountability, July 2023; Monument Lab (Art studio) (Box Electronic Records)
  Story by Paul M. Farber and Patricia Eunji Kim in the Monument Lab. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- Podcast Episode 30: A Crack in the Hourglass: An Ongoing COVID-19 Memorial with Rafael Lozano-Hemmer and Sekou Cooke (Live at the Brooklyn Museum), July 2023; Monument Lab (Art studio) (Box Electronic Records)
  Podcast episode of Future Memory from the Monument Lab on Lozano-Hemmer's A Crack in the Hourglass. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- MORE Caucus NYC, May 2020-March 2021; Movement of Rank and File Educators (Box Electronic Records)
  Movement of Rank and File Educators (MORE) is the social justice caucus of United Federation of Teachers (UFT) in New York City. The are an opposition group that offers themselves as a positive alternative to current union leadership. On April 8, 2020, MORE posted an open letter to Chancellor Carranza, Mayor De Blasio, and NYSED Interim Commissioner Shannon Tahoe proposing amendments to the City's emergency remote-learning plan for New York City Department of Education educators during the COVID-19 crisis. The letter calls for a slowdown in academics, a focus on trauma informed teaching, a suspension on grading for June report cards, support for the retention of a spring break, and more resources for public health initiatives.
- Health Justice Agenda, April 2022-ongoing; Movement of Rank and File Educators (Box Electronic Records)
  The Health Justice Agenda is a working group of the Movement of Rank and File Educators (MORE), a caucus of the UFT. The working group demanded full funding for schools and communities, health justice, and anti-racist approaches and training for all staff before they would return to work for in-person teaching.
- OneWorld COVID-19 Special Collection, July 2023; Museum of Chinese in the Americas (Box Electronic Records)
  Oral history project at the Museum of Chinese in America. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- Mutual Aid NYC, May 2020-ongoing (Box Electronic Records)
  Mutual Aid NYC is a network of groups organizing to provide aid and support in the midst of the COVID-19 pandemic. They are everyday New Yorkers working to lift up local organizing, connect people to resources, and build a citywide movement to address this crisis. Their members include parents, elders, immigrants, people with disabilities and chronic illness, caregivers, care workers, and other organizers. The page is fairly straightforward, with no AV. Most of the updates appear to be in the For Groups+ Organizers section, specifically the Find Resources + other groups page and the Case Studies page. Other sections include tips on using various social media platforms and collaborative tools and forms to request aid and to become a volunteer and donate to mutual aid groups.
- Mutual Aid NYC Community Resource Library, July 2021-ongoing; Mutual Aid NYC (Box Electronic Records)
  Resource library of New York City organization and programs developed by Mutual Aid NYC. The website is broken down into the following resource categories: Education, Housing, Money, Food, and Legal. It provides the name of the resource, the organization responsible for the resource, the website of the resource, contact information, location, and a description of the resource.
- Mutual Aid NYC Newsletter, July 2020-ongoing; Mutual Aid NYC (Box Electronic Records)
  A newsletter about mutual aid efforts around New York City by and for Mutual Aid NYC volunteers.
- Mutual Aid NYC Resource Lists, July 2022-ongoing; Mutual Aid NYC (Box Electronic Records)
  Resource lists curated by Mutual Aid NYC. Includes lists of support groups, New York City housing resources, helplines and hotlines, spanish resources, and LGBTQ resources.
- Home is a Human Right, April 2022-ongoing; Mutual Aid NYC (Box Electronic Records)
  Home is a Human Right, a project affiliated with Mutual AID NYC, is a collective of volunteers developing sustainable mutual aid models that address the crisis of unequal access to housing in New York City. Their projects include partnering with apartment seekers to confront racial and income discrimination in housing searches; sourcing and moving furniture to support people who finally do get housing; and using media to amplify the wisdom and vision of those who have first-hand experience with housing instability, as well as insights about how to end this crisis. Their website contains transcripts of their listening series and information on the projects.
- The Moving Support Project, April 2022-ongoing; Mutual Aid NYC (Box Electronic Records)
  The Moving Support Project, an affiliate of Mutual Aid NYC and a project of Housing is A Human Right, helps formerly unhoused people secure furniture to make their space into a home.
- Magnum Foundation, July 2023; The Nation, New York. (Box Electronic Records)
  Magnum Foundation is a nonprofit organization that expands creativity and diversity in documentary photography, activating new audiences and ideas through the innovative use of images. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- Covid Know More, July 2023; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (Box Electronic Records)
  COVID-19 explainer by the NAACP. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- 670,000 flags on the National Mall pay tribute to America's devastating COVID-19 losses, July 2023; National Geographic Partners (U.S.) (Box Electronic Records)
  Article by Rachel Hartigan in National Geographic. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- COVID-19 Guidance for People Who Use Drugs and Harm Reduction Programs, May 2020-March 2021; National Harm Reduction Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
  Harm Reduction Coalition is a bi-coastal network committed to drug user rights and overdose prevention. They aim to "challenge the persistent stigma faced by people who use drugs and advocate for policy and public health reform." The Harm Reduction Coalition's "COVID-19 Guidance for People Who Use Drugs" offers guides for safer drug use and harm reduction during the COVID-19 crisis. It also provides tips for community-based syringe services and need exchange providers. Guides are offered as links to PDF documents and are available in Portuguese, Arabic, and English.
- The COVID-19 Outbreak in the Navajo Nation, July 2023; National Museum of the American Indian (U.S.) (Box Electronic Records)
  Photo essay by Donovan Quintero in collaboration with the Smithsonian's National Museum of the American Indian. Website also contains an interview with Quintero. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- Developing Stories: Native Photographers in the Field, July 2023; National Museum of the American Indian (U.S.) (Box Electronic Records)
  Developing Stories: Native Photographers in the Field is a series of three photo essays created by Native photojournalists Donovan Quintero, Tailyr Irvine, and Russel Albert Daniels in collaboration with the Smithsonian's National Museum of the American Indian. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- The Tyranny of the ZIP Code, July 2023; The New republic (Box Electronic Records)
  Article by Anna Clark in the New Republic. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- New York City COVID-19 Action, May 2020-July 2021 (Box Electronic Records)
  This website is compiled by grassroots organizers based in New York City and serves to support and amplify local campaigns by issue areas so that anyone can find a campaign and get involved immediately. The site includes sections on healthcare, housing, prison abolition, debt relief, utilities, immigration, labor, and environmental justice. Each section includes several links to petitions, google documents, call scripts, and links to relief funds related to COVID-19.
- New York Immigration Coalition-COVID-19 Resources, May 2020-January 2023; New York Immigration Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
  The New York Immigration Coalition (NYIC) is a policy and advocacy umbrella organization that represents immigrant and refugee rights groups across New York. Membership in NYIC is inclusive of labor unions, academic institutions, religious groups, legal organizations, and socio economic justice organizations. The NYIC COVID-19 Resources websites provides links to one-page PDF briefs with information on how COVID-19 affects health, education, immigration, social services, and civic engagement in New York. Documentation is translated into eight languages inclusive of Spanish, Arabic, Bengali, Korean, Chinese, Haitian Creole, Russian, and English. The website also provides links to PDF community toolkits that share know-your-rights information, food bank information, mental health and domestic violence resources, and information on reporting hate crimes.The website also offers links to PDFs describing access to COVID-19 testing, evaluation, and treatment services covered by Medicaid.
- New York Immigration Coalition COVID-19 NYC Resources, August 2020-ongoing; New York Immigration Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
- New York Immigration Coalition COVID Education Resources, October 2020-ongoing; New York Immigration Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
- New York Immigration Coalition COVID Employment Resources, October 2020-ongoing; New York Immigration Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
- New York Immigration Coalition COVID Financial Resources, October 2020-ongoing; New York Immigration Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
- New York Immigration Coalition COVID Food Resources, October 2020-ongoing; New York Immigration Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
- New York Immigration Coalition COVID Healthcare Resources, October 2020-ongoing; New York Immigration Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
- New York Immigration Coalition COVID Small Business Resources, October 2020-ongoing; New York Immigration Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
- New York Immigration Coalition List: NYC COVID-19 Resources & Services, May 2020-ongoing; New York Immigration Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
  Google sheet with COVID-19 resources and services compiled by the New York Immigration Coalition (NYIC). The spreadsheet is organized by FAQs, education, employment, finances, food, health care, and small business.
- New York Immigration Coalition: NYC COVID-19 Resources & Services, October 2020-ongoing; New York Immigration Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
- Take Action to Support All New Yorkers, May 2020-February 2022; New York Immigration Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
  Petition put together by the New York Immigration Coalition to support the New York United campaign to ensure immigrants in New York State remain healthy and safe during the COVID-19 pandemic.
- New York State Nurses Association COVID-19 Resources, May 2020-ongoing; New York State Nurses Association (Box Electronic Records)
  The New York State Nurses Association is a union of 42,000 frontline nurses. They are New York's largest union and professional association for registered nurses. Their COVID-19 Resources page has daily updates that include tributes to nurses who were victims of COVID-19, forms for nurses who want to protest their assignment, FAQs related to sick leave and testing safety, and preparedness checklists, vaccine and booster information, COVID variants, mask guidance, and safe staffing. The page also encourages nurses to participate in a daily diary project, and several links to petitions.
- New York State Nurses Association Videos, January 2023-ongoing; New York State Nurses Association (Box Electronic Records)
  Videos from the nurses strike in January 2023.
- We Love NY Nurses, November 2022-ongoing; New York State Nurses Association (Box Electronic Records)
  We Love NY Nurses is the New York State Nurses Association's contract campaign garnering support for New York State nurses and healthcare professionals with expiring contracts at the end of 2022 and early 2023. The website contains their demands for safe staffing and benefits, as well as a pledge for support.
- President Trump: Use the Defense Production Act to get frontline healthcare workers armor in the battle against COVID-19 Petition, May 2020-February 2022; New York State Nurses Association (Box Electronic Records)
  Petition compiled by New York State Nurses Association on increasing supply of personal protection equipment.
- Tell Governor Cuomo: Implement NYSNA's COVID-19 Surge Action Plan! Petition, May 2020-February 2022; New York State Nurses Association (Box Electronic Records)
  Petition compiled by New York State Nurses Association on creating a COVID-19 surge action plan.
- A Covid Epicenter Hustles Back to Life: 'What You See, It's Survival', July 2023; New York Times Company (Box Electronic Records)
  New York Times article by Annie Correal and photographs by Victor J. Blue. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- Covid Memorials Offer a Place to Put Our Grief, July 2023; New York Times Company (Box Electronic Records)
  New York Times article by Jillian Steinhauer on art exhibitions related to pandemic losses. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- Dancing Through New York in a Summer of Joy and Grief, July 2023; New York Times Company (Box Electronic Records)
  Article by Carina del Valle Schorske in the New York Times. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- Four Studies of Black Healing, July 2023; New York Times Company (Box Electronic Records)
  Photo essays by Gioncarlo Valentine and Elliott Jerome Brown Jr. in the New York Times. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- If You're Suffering After Being Sick With Covid, It's Not Just in Your Head, July 2023; New York Times Company (Box Electronic Records)
  Article Zeynep Tufekci in the New York Times. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- 'It's Not Enough': Living Through a Pandemic on $100 a Week, July 2023; New York Times Company (Box Electronic Records)
  New York Times article by Annie Correal and Desiree Rios. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- Scarred by Covid, Survivors and Victims' Families Aim to Be a Political Force, July 2023; New York Times Company (Box Electronic Records)
  Article by Sheryl Gay Stolberg in the New York Times. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- Stories From the Great American Labor Shortage, July 2023; New York Times Company (Box Electronic Records)
  Episode of the New York Times "Daily" podcast. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- These 115 Workers Helped Keep New York Alive in Its Darkest Months, July 2023; New York Times Company (Box Electronic Records)
  Article by Todd Heisler and David Gonzalez in the New York Times. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- What if America Had Learned From New York City?, July 2023; New York Times Company (Box Electronic Records)
  Article by Mara Gay in the New York Times. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- What Loss Looks Like, July 2023; New York Times Company (Box Electronic Records)
  Virtual COVID-19 memorial by Dani Blum and Jaspal Riyait in the New York Times. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- Why New York Needs a Covid Memorial, July 2023; New York Times Company (Box Electronic Records)
  Opinion article by the editorial board of the New York Times. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- History as it Happens: Rescuing the Historical Record in a Digital World, July 2023; New York University (Box Electronic Records)
  Article by Sarah Binney at NYU News. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- A/P/A Voices: A COVID-19 Public Memory Project, July 2023; New York University. Asian/Pacific/American Studies Program and Institute (Box Electronic Records)
  Project framing statement for the COVID-19 Public Memory Project at the A/P/A Institute at NYU. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- Disability Covid Chronicles, July 2023; New York University. Center for Disability Studies (Box Electronic Records)
  Disability Covid Chronicles documents the "disability communities that have been disproportionately impacted by city and national policies, work and housing conditions, stigma, racism, and violence as much as the virus itself. In the shadow of "risk," we report on a variety of disability experiences including incarceration, low wage and essential work, maternal mental health, anti-Asian violence, senior centers, migrant detention centers, Long Covid, public schools, the MTA, blindness and digital accessibility, caregiving, arts workers, and the Black Lives Matter protests." The website contains their digital archive, research, articles, and other resources. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- #NoBodyIsDisposable Know Your Rights Guide to Surviving COVID-19 Triage Protocols, June 2020-February 2022; NoBody Is Disposable Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
  Google document linked from the SWOP Brooklyn website's COVID resource page. Toolkit for people facing potential COVID-19 triage discrimination based on disability or weight.
- NYC COVID Care, June 2020-April 2022; NYC Covid Care Network (Box Electronic Records)
  NYC COVID Care is a mutual aid network comprised of therapists, psychiatrists, counselors, life coaches, grief counselors, spiritual care providers, organizers, and crisis line workers. They focus on facilitating individual support encounters, support groups, stress-reduction trainings, and grief and loss rituals. All individual support meetings happen by video or telephone. They make it clear that they are not offering therapy, but are connecting individuals for care and support. Some of the individuals involved in the project are licensed therapists, professionally certified to offer therapeutic services. As consenting adults, participants are encouraged to construct the relationship that feels most helpful. Once they connect individuals, the interaction is outside the network.
- NYC United Against Coronavirus, May-November 2020 (Box Electronic Records)
  NYC United Against Coronavirus is run by a group of volunteers who have set up a Google Doc, an email address, a Twitter account, an Instagram, and a Facebook page. The Google Doc provides a fairly comprehensive list of mutual aid actions and organizations across NYC. Sections include Immediate Needs (pg. 2-18), Get Organized, Advocacy, Local Information, and Other Resources. The list also includes links to the list in other languages (Spanish, Mandarin, Korean, with more languages coming soon). The doc is mostly made up of links to different forms, websites, social media accounts, and email addresses.
- NYC United Against Coronavirus, November 2020-July 2021 (Box Electronic Records)
- NYC Veterans Alliance, June 2020-February 2022 (Box Electronic Records)
  NYC Veterans Alliance exists to "empower veterans, families, and civilian allies to connect as a community, advocate for improved policies, and advance as civic leaders." Beginning in mid-March 2020, NYC Veterans Alliance started the Veterans Mutual Aid project to support veterans and their families with facing the realities of the pandemic, from housing insecurity to food scarcity. The Veterans Mutual Aid project includes information on tenants rights, workers rights, food and financial assistance, and support for veterans benefits claims during COVID-19. It also provides links to mental health assistance and ways to support others and stay connected during the crisis.
- Meeting the Moment: Socially Engaged Performance, 1965–2020, by Those Who Lived It, July 2023; NYU Press (Box Electronic Records)
  Catalog entry for Meeting the Moment by Jan Cohen-Cruz and Rad Pereira. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- The Opportunity Atlas, July 2023 (Box Electronic Records)
  The Opportunity Atlas is a data project that documents which neighborhoods in America offer children the best chance to rise out of poverty. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.
- Half Assed Disabled Prepper Tips for Preparing for a Coronavirus Quarantine, June 2020-February 2022; Piepzna-Samarasinha, Leah Lakshmi, 1975- (Box Electronic Records)
  Google document linked from the SWOP Brooklyn website's COVID resource page. Toolkit for disabled people to prepare for COVID-19 quarantine.
- Utilities Strike Toolkit, May 2020-February 2022; Public Power Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
  Toolkit linked from the New York City COVID-19 Action campaign list. The toolkit calls for a strike of utility bills during the COVID-19 pandemic.
- Queens Memory Podcast, July 2023; Queens Borough Public Library (Box Electronic Records)
  Podcast highlighting oral histories as part of the Queens Public Library collections. Season 2 documented Queens residents during the COVID-19 pandemic and Season 3 featured stories from Queens' Asian American communities. A resource featured on the Zip Code Memory Project website.